Let's say you're trying to lose 20 pounds,
or boost your immunity,
or increase your ability to fight COVID,
or even cancer.
Well, the amazing thing is,
with the right diet,
you're well on your way to
achieving these vital health goals.
Welcome to the Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I'm your host, Dr. Michael Greger.
Today it’s all about the gut,
otherwise known as the gastrointestinal tract.
And we’ll start with a study
that looks at the microbiome
of those eating plant based diets.
Almost 2,500 years ago,
Hippocrates stated that
“All disease begins in the gut.”
Feed our gut bacteria right,
with whole plant-foods,
and they feed us right back
with beneficial compounds
like butyrate, which gut
bugs make from fiber.
Feed them wrong, on the other
hand, and they can produce
detrimental compounds like
TMAO, which our gut bugs
make from cheese, seafood,
eggs, and meat.
Now we used to think that
TMAO only contributed to
cardiovascular diseases, like
heart disease and stroke,
but more recently it has
been linked to everything from
psoriatic arthritis to
polycystic ovary syndrome.
I’m most concerned about
our leading killers, though.
If you look at the top ten
causes of death in the United States,
we know about heart disease
and stroke, killers #1 and #5,
but recently, an association
has been between blood levels
of TMAO and the risks of
various cancers, killer #2.
It could be the inflammation
caused by TMAO that explains
the link between TMAO and
cancer, but it could also be
oxidative stress such as
free radicals, DNA damage,
or a disruption in protein folding.
Killer #4 are chronic
obstructive pulmonary diseases
like emphysema, and TMAO is
associated with premature death
in patients with exacerbated COPD,
though they suspect it’s
just due to them dying
from more cardiovascular disease.
The link to stroke is a
no-brainer—no pun intended—
because of the higher
blood pressure associated
with higher TMAO levels as
well as the greater likelihood
of clot formation in
those with atrial fibrillation.
And those with higher TMAO
levels also appear to have
worse strokes and four
times the odds of death.
Killer #6 is Alzheimer’s disease.
Does TMAO even get up into the brain?
Yes, TMAO is present in
human cerebrospinal fluid,
which bathes the brain, and
indeed the levels are higher
in both those with mild
cognitive dysfunction
and those with Alzheimer’s
disease dementia.
In the brain, TMAO has been shown
to induce neuronal senescence
(meaning deterioration with age),
increased oxidative stress
and impaired mitochondrial function,
all of which may contribute
to brain aging and cognitive impairment.
Killer #7 is diabetes, and
people with higher TMAO levels
are approximately 50% more
likely to have diabetes too.
Killer #8 is pneumonia, and
TMAO predicts fatal outcomes
in pneumonia patients even
without evident heart disease.
Killer #9 is kidney disease,
and TMAO is strongly related
to kidney function and predicts
fatal outcomes there as well.
Over a period of five years,
more than a half of chronic kidney
disease patients who started
out with an average or higher
TMAO levels were dead,
whereas among those in the
lowest third of levels,
nearly 90% remain alive.
Okay, so how can we lower the
TMAO levels in our blood?
Because TMAO originates from
dietary sources, we could limit
our intake of choline and
carnitine-rich foods,
but they’re "so widespread", we’re
talkin’ meat, eggs, and dairy.
Therefore, restriction of foods
rich in TMAO-creating nutrients
may not be practical.
I mean, can’t we just get
a vegan fecal transplant?
Vegan donors were kind
enough to provide
the investigators with
a fresh morning sample.
If you remember, if you
give a vegan a steak,
despite all the carnitine in the meat,
they make almost no TMAO
compared to a meat-eater, presumably
because they haven’t been
fostering steak-eating
bugs in their gut.
Remarkably, even if you give
plant-based eaters the equivalent
of a 20-ounce steak
every day for two months,
only about half start ramping
up production of TMAO
showing just how far their
gut flora had to change.
The capacity of veggie feces to
churn out TMAO is almost nonexistent.
So, instead of eating healthier,
why not just get
some of that sweet vegan
poop off the brown market.
In a double-blind, randomized,
controlled trial,
research subjects either got vegan
poop or their own poop back.
The complete stool production
was stirred—not shaken—
and then infused through
a hose down their nose,
and . . . it didn’t work.
First of all, the vegans they
recruited for their study
started out making TMAO themselves,
as opposed to the other study
where they didn’t make any at all.
This may be because the other
study required the vegans
to have been plant-based for
at least a year, and this study didn’t.
So yeah, not much of a change in
TMAO running through their bodies
two weeks after getting the vegan poop,
but the vegan poop they got
seemed to start out with some capacity
to produce TMAO in the first place.
So, the failure to improve after
the vegan fecal transplant
could be related to limited
baseline microbiome differences
as well as the continuation of an
omnivorous diet after the transplant.
What’s the point of trying
to reset your microbiome
if you’re just going to eat meat?
Well, the researchers didn’t
want to switch people
to a plant-based diet since
they knew that alone can change
your microbiome, and they didn’t
want to introduce any extra factors.
Bottom line—no pun intended—
it looks like there may
not be any shortcuts.
We may just have to
eat a healthier diet.
Did you know that more
than half of IBS sufferers
(irritable bowel syndrome)
appear to have a form of atypical food allergy?
Here’s the story.
Irritable bowel syndrome (IBS) is
a chronic gastrointestinal disorder
that affects about one in ten.
You may have heard about
those low-FODMAP diets,
but they don't appear to work any better
than the standard advice to avoid things
like coffee or spicy and fatty foods; in
fact, you can hardly tell which is which.
But most IBS patients do seem to react
to specific foods, such as wheat, dairy,
soy sauce, or eggs, though when
you test them for typical food allergies,
they may come up negative on a skin
prick test. But what you want to know
is not what happens on their skin but
inside their gut when you eat them.
Enter confocal laser endomicroscopy.
How cool is this?
You can snake a microscope down
someone's throat into their gut
and drip on some foods
and watch in real-time
as the gut wall becomes
inflamed and leaky.
You can actually see the
cracks forming within minutes.
But it had never been
tested on a largeÂgroup
of IBS patients until now.
Using this new technology,
researchers found that more
than half of IBS sufferers have
this kind of reaction to various foods,
what they call an atypical food allergy,
that flies under the radar
of traditional allergy tests.
Exclude those foods from the diet,
and you get a significant alleviation
of symptoms. But outside of
a research setting, there's no way
to know which foods are the culprit
without trying your own exclusion diet.
And there's no greater exclusion
diet than excluding everything.
A 25-year-old woman had complained of
abdominal pain, bloating, and diarrhea
for a year, and drugs didn't seem
to help. But after fasting for 10 days,
her symptoms improved considerably
and appeared to stay that way
at least 18 months later. And it
wasn't just subjective improvement.
They took biopsies that showed
the inflammation go down,
directly measured her bowel irritability,
and stuck expanding balloons
and electrodes in her rectum
to actually measure changes
in her sensitivity to pressure
and electrical stimulation.
Fasting seemed to
kind of reboot her gut,
but just because it worked for her
doesn't mean it works for others.
Case reports are most useful when they
inspire researchers to put it to the test.
Despite research efforts, medical
treatment for this condition
is still unsatisfactory.
We can try to suppress
the symptoms with drugs,
but what do you do when
even that doesn't work?
Eighty-four IBS patients, 58 of whom
who failed basic treatment
which consisted of pharmacotherapy
and brief psychotherapy,
36 of the 58 who were still suffering
underwent 10 days of fasting,
whereas the other 22 stuck
with the basic treatment.
And those in the fasting group
experienced significant improvements
in abdominal pain, diarrhea,
loss of appetite, nausea, anxiety,
and interference with life in general,
which was significantly better
than the control group.
The researchers concluded that
fasting therapy could be useful
for treating moderate to
severe patients with IBS.
Unfortunately, patient allocation was
neither blinded nor randomized,
so the comparison to the
control group doesn't mean much.
They were also given IV vitamins---
B1 and vitamin C---
which seems typical of these
Japanese fasting trials,
even though one wouldn't expect to
get vitamin deficiency syndromes---
beriberi or scurvy---to present
within just 10 days of fasting.
And they were also kept isolated,
and maybe that made the
psychotherapy work better?
It's hard to tease out just the fasting
effects. Psychotherapy alone can provide
lasting benefits. One hundred and one
outpatients with irritable bowel
syndrome were randomized to medical
treatment or medical treatment
with three months of psychotherapy.
After three months, the psychotherapy
group did better, and the difference
was even more pronounced a year later---
a year after the psychotherapy ended.
Better at 3 months and
even better at 15 months.
Psychological approaches appear
to work about as well
as antidepressant drugs for IBS,
but the placebo response for
IBS is on the order of 40%,
and that's whether we're talking
about psychological interventions
or drugs or alternative
medicine approaches.
So essentially nothing---a sugar pill---
improves symptoms 40% of the time.
So I figure one might as well choose a
therapy first that's cheap, safe, simple,
and side effect free, which extended
fasting is most certainly not. But if all
else fails, it may be worth exploring
under close physician supervision.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social media
to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts Podcast
landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics
you can order the e-book, audio book,
or hard copy of my latest book
“How to Survive a Pandemic.”
For recipes, check out my
“How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Which is my latest-latest book.
It’s beautifully designed, with more than 100
recipes for delicious and nutritious meals.
All the proceeds I receive from
the sales of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.